all right we're on
officially welcome welcome everybody
um and welcome back johannes
be honest as we as we like to tease is
the um
the uh the weirder the weirder
philosopher on the internet
and and i've uh i've enjoyed i've really
just enjoyed
actually after reading heidegger on my
own for years and years and years
right and not knowing anyone else that
really
understood heidegger um having met you
and being able to talk about this stuff
has
just been really has has been just
awesome
so i love all of our conversation i get
a lot of really good feedback every time
every time you're on the channel and
you're also you're also started doing
courses on the on the internet um and
i've taken a couple of them
and there i re i actually think
whether or not you're this was your
intention or not i actually think that
you're
in some way you're innovating a new
a new way of doing things as a
philosopher um
and because it seems like you're what
you're what you're offering
are things that are i mean there's
i don't know if it can get any more less
instrumental
right then and and useful or practical
than
philosophy i mean almost by definition
philosophy isn't that
um and so you're you're
let's see are you still there you look a
little frozen
so we're having a few technical
difficulties just so for people who are
watching
internet's a little spotty apparently in
london and i'm in a new place
and um i'm at an airbnb uh
in santa barbara on the ocean with
i have a bunch of rugrats running around
so we may get disturbed on many
different levels with the video so i'll
just
i'll just pause it and so but the the
recording may be a little choppy
but we'll make do with what we got um
well i
i think what i was saying is that i
actually think that whether or not
you're this was i don't think this was
your intention but
you making these offerings on the
internet and teaching online yeah
right is as i was saying that on one
level it's
people who are taking it are taking
something that probably is by definition
the least um
immediately useful or instrumental right
and that
philosophy by definition is is that
realm and which isn't
it's it addresses what has things show
up
such that they're useful in the first
place right
yeah yeah so so that you're getting such
a good response
and such good feedback on this i think
is showing
that you're one of the rare places where
people can start to
like in and it's the closing window i
think in my view
of where people can come and actually
learn
learn and discuss and have their minds
blown about things
that have no immediate for for its own
sake in a certain sense
and i i have a sense of feeling is it is
is quite innovative
innovative that way
yes thank you i mean it's going back um
so the one of the courses you were in
was
the heidige course on death and being
yeah um and i think you you had time for
some of the seminars too the course that
starts next week
is on nietzsche and it will run for
seven weeks
and um i'll give
anyone who listens on on this channel
the same as
on mine if people enroll now
you get 50 off so we can leave something
maybe
just down below in the comments
um so they can enroll on this platform
that i'm using
and i had a couple of a couple of things
on what you just said i had a
conversation with the josh uh hochschild
i think that's how you pronounce it it's
actually a chairman named hochschild
i think his family is from frankfurt
he's american he teaches
at the catholic college a liberal arts
college
he's you know he's a he teaches in a
very classical styles it's about
changing he said to me you're on the on
the on the edge
of the cutting edge of what's
what's possible online um and i don't
know it was
i mean that was not the intention that i
had obviously what i
in my mind there was the only intention
that i had was
i want to teach that's all i know
right and uh so just that's why i
started
the channel and um just to
be able to give the lectures in the way
that i
want to some of the stranger ones
attracted to you
which should be
i should be quite telling the horrible
audio quality
video was even worse um
not even even speaking of the content of
course just but
yeah so and then it over the course of
the last 2019 actually it got
it got some traction um and then people
started
signing up for it you know patreon or
some even you know came for and wanted
to talk to me for about
one of them for more than half a year
spoke with me
um spoke for about six
six hours every month um
and my the the academy i'm building
it's got a has got two light motifs if
you like
one of them is a quote from shelling the
german philosopher
which is this learn only in order to
create
but he says the full quote is that all
rules for study
summed up in this one learn only in
order to
to create and that's why you know
there are no credentials there's no
pieces of paper even though that would
be
you know could be quite funny to have
sort of a as
a fake certificate or something but it
is
completely non-instrumental yes it's
it's free from
from any demands um in that regard
there's there's nothing attached to it
there's no certain prestige
uh that comes with you cannot gain
status but you what what happens one of
the things for example is
let's come out of the two courses one of
them on idleness with dignity that's
also very important
right the the motto the other light
motif is
dignitary idleness with dignity which is
another way of saying a system an old
latin
saying from cicero it just means that
there is no you can still earn dignity
in a non-instrumental environment
and what's led to for example with
someone who's
taken both courses now he's found
his lifetime writing project that he
wants to write on
through the courses someone else
always apparently for years and years
and years wanted to read philosophy
had bought all the books but as you know
it's
a bit overwhelming sometimes and
he's now gone from taking the courses to
becoming a private student
and we go through his writings together
he writes essays
and i give him comments on those essays
and it's probably going to develop into
a longer piece
this time actually than on nietzsche um
on on
the tragic tragic existence in nietzsche
and that's thing that comes out of this
but it's pure that this it's purely for
lit because people find i don't know why
but people find it within themselves
they want to
write i mean i know why i i i need to do
it myself i write
all the time right i've written this
extremely strange poem here from tree to
tree
um which i recorded a couple weeks ago i
wrote this in february
and it just comes out and it and i think
once you yeah so uh
once you kind of divide it from from
from the
from the instrumental it's it becomes
something where it perhaps
should have been anyways it's free
it's a free endeavor and it's
peripatetic in that sense right it's um
it's it's
taking a a walk together in in thinking
rather than um wanting you know one of
the strangest things you have to do in
university is you have to give learning
outcomes at the beginning of a seminar
i don't know how that's what that's you
know there's no learning outcome
there's not a factory yeah and
someone someone asked recently what
about ammo fati and nietzsche and how
can we apply this
someone asked us in the live stream he
said no no there's no application
it happens in thinking it through and as
you think it
you become it but you become this way of
thinking
yeah yeah totally and it's like there's
a sense in which
i mean this is actually uh you you
contributed a chapter i just got done
finishing my chapter finally um on our
anthology with
with with verveiki and chris and about
about dialogos but one of the things i i
did was
um i really and i had no idea i was
going to
such a degree about nihilism right and
but
once i started about it it just became
what
i really saw in a deep way how it was
underlying
everything in a way in a way that
nihilism itself couldn't account for
and and i that's what strikes me as
unique about what you're doing is that
it's showing one that there's that that
is far i mean as far as that we can
as far as we know right human beings
through thought right are the one are
the one way in which
um you can access the world as such and
and to into into to philosophize and to
think that way
is in some sense saying it's it's it's
it's saying which is
something that's really disappearing the
sense of that there's a being and an
intelligence and being
and that there's a way to listen the
thinking is a kind of listening
and perceiving that
that acknowledges that there's something
hidden and that thinking
that philosophy is a way of bringing
something um
that's hidden out in the open in that in
that sense
that that being has intelligibility
um of and beyond its our own consumption
of it
um is is that
that loss of that sense is nihilism um
and so i think philosophy is one of the
few ways that
that people can actually come into that
understanding of being through the
through the act of philosophizing
and so that's why i think it's so
striking that people are
that what you're actually offering is
something um
that's outside of it's outside of or
different or other than nihilism in ways
that people probably can't even
know to articulate i mean like
that maybe you could turn off your
microphone and get an echo
one of the things i so one of the things
that's strange
is um
it's having to at all having to explain
what it is that philosophy achieves
philosophy is not some strange
abstraction
uh philosophy is not uh
philosophy is an articulation of
actuality of the cliche or if you like
reality which is not the term
most often used and not just that it's
it's it's a it articulates the way we
access the world right
it um without philosophy there is
we don't have access to the world to
what it means
to be on as well and
nihilism is when you look at someone
like nietzsche uh nihilism for nietzsche
is
some is one of the
one of the one of the results of the
death of god
but also of um
of of a you know a christian morality
that wanted to deny life
that's the first consequence of morals
and the last consequence
morality wants to deny everything and
denying
life and that means to deny
suffering etc if that is furniture
that's lionel has been at least to an
utter destruction
and the the nihilism that he sees is
that
it will be um it will be the history for
the next 200 years
but now on on on what
you just said
a bit more um
philosophy is not i will say it again
it's it's
easier to say what philosophy is not um
is not something that arbitrarily we we
can choose to do or not to do and i
highly assess this quite often he says
you know
whether we have heard of certain
thoughts or not does not matter
and as nietzsche says in sarathustra
thoughts that come
on dove's feet guide the world
these are almost silent thoughts
they guide the world i mean no no no i
would probably
here's an outrageous claim most people
will never have heard of descartes
um certainly you know people who listen
to to you and this
channel they will have heard of rene
descartes
um and of the cartesian subjective
subjectivity etc but most haven't
and still it's it's that's the that's
the self
understanding of most people in the west
and now
beyond and if your self
understanding is even if you haven't
articulated it like this
that i am the positive ego
off in my world
and i'm looking for certainty
and that i can posit that certainty over
object
over the world or objects of and over
the world
then i'm like you know simplifying
things and i'm a cathedral subject
even without ever having heard of this
name because i'm simply as highly i
would put it
thrown into this um into this
history that i have to accept as my own
and what we can learn from a thinker
like nietzsche is that we are you know
really at the
at he says the destiny is growing
right and someone like nietzsche who is
who does not have the releasement of
heidegger who was
glass and about letting go especially an
old age
he would probably run around screaming
and he could see what we're doing
because he said no we have to transvalue
all values we cannot come back to
uh um a christian
morality without christianity
right so the the entire neuroscience
nonsense about
let's reduce suffering etc that to
nietzsche that's just christianity in
disguise
and he's also the the death of god of
which he speaks
nietzsche isn't nietzsche wants to find
an f
a way of affirming life and here's a
beautiful
what what does life mean for nietzsche
life he says
is everything that we are
including our shadows and everything
that hits us
that meets us that affects us if we are
able to transfigure
all of this into light and flame that's
a direct quote
then that's life so what is supposed to
be affirmed
with nietzsche is this profound sense of
suffering
um and then move and then
hopefully be able to move through
nihilism in this
manner and artistically so as well so
perhaps you know to bring this back to
the uh beginning of this
dialogue um there is a certain artistic
element to what i do
i would say um which as you know i'm a
musician i don't know if anyone
maybe i'll put this up here's my guitar
i don't know if the
actually the camera is good enough so i
make music
um and it's you know it is quite
liberating actually to
you have to turn your microphone again
sorry
and you write poetry
yes i write poetry i write songs uh
i play guitar i'm just learning i'm
teaching myself how to play the piano
uh so you know you have to blame the
lock down for that
it's going to be another so i make music
under a pseudonym
um and it's it's
the strange thing is this i always felt
that there is something overarching
about technology
the more heidegger you read and the more
nietzsche you read
and others you realize you know the
the way out of the cave is
to go deeper into the cave so the way
out of
you know there is no way out of of of
technology i mean one of the best
um one of the best examples is ted
kaczynski
i mean he was so right and he's he's
becoming a hero again for which i
i would not um i would not support
uh he all he ever thought about he was
so anti that he became
i don't know did he actually kill
someone i mean he sent
you know he he became quite violent
um and and all he thought of
was technology right what were
technological tools
so he was completely unfree in this
relationship with it
nietzsche says somewhere in in the
unpublished
or the posthumously published notebooks
that the ubermensch
is the one who the overman is the one
who is
who is ready and ripe to deal with
technology
and i realized over the years that you
know you you can
it can be it can get you down
because then you're you know as you know
you know you you you
it's a death by numbers you're evaluated
the entire time
um and especially also when you have
just
you know so i but then i realized by
going
through by just really enough uploading
a few videos on youtube
and not caring about numbers like how
many hits how many likes
how many doesn't matter none of it
matters what matters is there's a
genuine project
that needs to be articulated and then
shared
and that usually leads to something if
it's not
completely nothing right and so it's it
is quite
it's very playful this whole thing and
this is what i'm learning again with
reading nietzsche now is this
the the the playful attitude towards
life
which is for him that the apollonian in
the mix with the dionysian right so we
are
playing with with these tools you are
doing this as well
obviously um and and but only to
to incr almost you know we can almost
say increase our freedom or liberate
ourselves more and
be not letting us get down or
be ruled by it so i find that very
exhilarating i find it
really fascinating what that this is
what because you know you
you could just look at these things the
entire time and
and be kind of be dominated
by the machine yeah yeah
but no i mean no one when they started
youtube i mean no one no one thought
that this would happen
i mean it was it was for cats let's just
you know it was
people were uploading cat videos that
was
yeah totally it's totally rogue right
they were the beginning
they're the beginning internet
philosophers
and they would just go at each other it
was a prayer apparently it's pretty
ruthless the guy um cory anton is one of
the
uh one of the first people who got on
there and started talking about
philosophy and he talks a lot about that
i've had him on the channel a couple of
times but you know
i'm gonna go back to something that you
said that
about this connection between there's
something about philosophy and art
right and especially making art that has
a set there's
they come from a similar root of some
kind
and i have to say i was struck by in
writing
so this was my first venture into
writing kind of an academic
like paper um i went to art school and
all that stuff i never really just
i i just never was that never was asked
of me
so i i wasn't sure exactly how this was
going to go but i was quite struck
and it felt it almost exactly like
painting and sculpting it almost felt
exactly like that
and and why a particular part of it
because
if you you know if you ask people who
aren't painters and sculptors and stuff
to think about like a a
a studio of people painting let's say
usually they have they have a tendency
to think they picture
people with paint brushes painting on a
canvas
but actually if you go into an actual
painting studio
you know in this and i went to the one
of the best art schools in the world
like the most avant-garde
you know ones in the world and what you
saw was not people painting but you
asked
you saw people standing back and looking
at their painting from different angles
and going like this
and listening to some kind of obscure
classical music
right and then every hour or so they may
come up and just do one little brush
stroke and they sit back
right and it was very it's very little
actual
painting as in as in right
creating in that sense it is much more
of a sense and i really get this and i
think people who do art will will
you know if they look they they'll
probably agree is like it's it's more
like
you're in you're in a relationship where
the authority is
is the painting and the stroke
that you always have an idea for like
some idea
what you want the what the stroke that
you the next stroke
to do what you think it wants to do but
then it pushes back
and there's an intelligibility in the
painting that's never exactly what you
actually put down
and you have to contend with that and i
found that to be the case
the same sense about writing this paper
is
i get clear about something i write a
sentence down to articulate it and then
in writing and i realized something
wasn't totally complete or that it
highlighted something i didn't mean it
to you but
absolutely that said something that's
that's why there cannot be learning
outcomes
right so that that's that's why i mean
if you give learning outcomes at the
beginning of a philosophy class
you have destroyed thinking then what
you do
is exactly this oh the apollonian that's
the rational and the dionysian that's
the irrational here's your schema and
now operate with that right
and heidegger is all about concealment
and that's with unconsumed another
schema
no get rid of these schemas once you
start reading a book
by a text behind it on a lithia
you have to begin to think and once you
start reading
nietzsche's birth of tragedy birth of
tragedy birth
what i'm realizing as i'm writing this
now is
that nietzsche is all about birth he
wants to
help we've you you're you're a great
reader of rilke
right it speaks of the arrow and the bow
and the tension and the energies in the
beginning we read this together
yeah um the second lg first lgm
and the so what you uh um
what do you realize is you know what
once you start reading the birth of
tragedy you have to think with him that
there is no schema of rational against
irrational no
the apollonian is um
if you begin to think it through what is
it it's a dreamlike
atmosphere within which there is still
measure and limitation so
you're already beginning to
think in a certain way and you get rid
of schemas there is no and this is the
same when you
when there's a genuine writing i mean
you could write a philosophical
academic essay um which is just you know
in this essay i will argue that p
and then you put everything into that
procrustas bed
um but that's not what we're trying to
do we're trying to articulate
with nature we're trying to articulate
life and existence
and that's this is why i really love
these
um these posthumously published notes by
him
so there are some of those have been
translated into english but not in the
you know i have to be very strict again
not in the proper sense
uh because they're not chronologically
done um
as the addition now what i will do for
the courses i will
translate a lot of those and they will
be in the lectures
one of them here's one of them on the
death of god because it reminded me
that's why i wanted to mention it when
you mentioned the
common root of poetry and philosophy
so he says what if at some point you
know as we have killed
god which is the the holiest
the most powerful the mightiest of all
how can we find solace if once a human
being actually begins to realize what it
means to have killed god
and then he asks must he that means you
know how does someone like this
find solace and cleanse himself must he
not be
or must he not become himself the
almightiest
and holiest poet
of all um so there's
in nietzsche like the call to to poetry
of course he's greek so he he knows
greek so he knows that poises
where we get the word poetry from in
english
is is
the is one way of of
generating a world and that's that's
what
what nietzsche is about right the life
affirmation is about generating
a new world is about generating a new
world
that could lead over and beyond
the last man and the last man fits in
nicely with
instruments
lost your sound okay
oh can you hear me again i can hear you
now you're good
okay sorry so i don't know where i was
um
where did it start the last man you're
going to translate at a
special sp
here for the first time translated into
english by
live no no no i mean this this is
um so what i mentioned here was that
uh the the the human being who
finally realized that that god is dead
will have to become an extremely
powerful poet and that means
someone who is able to generate a world
or meaning almost you could almost say
and of course that that's got problems
attached to it but
um but here the last man is actually
to come back to something you said
before is one of instrumental
rationality
is because all that matters for
the last man is an increase
in an extended material happiness
yeah yeah um and
it's it's about extending right you know
it's
extending the years that we live you
know
over you know prolonging
um life whereas nietzsche being a good
greek
is about an orgastic uh
explosion of high culture just for a
moment but also it's one of the things i
just love about nietzsche is this
you know what he says in twilight of the
idols
the worst question that we can ask a 23
a young man today is which career or
which profession which
job as if he continues by the age of 23
one were already finished and then he
goes on to say
one is a child um
at 30 in high culture
so yeah you read that's
nowhere to be found that you're still
young
that there's still time um
and time to develop and find and
explore rather than for him that's a
sign of decay of nihilism too right this
kind of
the busyness and having to produce and
over researching over analyzing uh
historicizing everything
so yeah it's it's making you know
making available the world because you
mentioned
nihilism making everything available is
itself
a nihilistic approach because it it
destroys
the beauty of the world and what is it
that a poet does
let's come back to maybe what heidegger
says what is it that a poet does for
heidegger or
a painter a painter for heiliger does
not represent anything
a good painter a good painter brings
forth a world
let's shine something that's literally
there
but often covered over right just that
that sense
just that sense of bringing forth right
i i hear in that i hear in that that is
on one level
it's a it's a completely different way
of perceiving
right because i think most of our worlds
are produced
right yeah but this sense of bringing
forth the world just that just that
place of coming from was something right
it seems to presuppose i hear in that
that
that there's that there's something
hidden there's something concealed
and that which is most concealed
probably demarcates not it's whether or
not it exists or not
right but but a kind of intelligibility
that with that with gumption
with devotion with a certain from a
certain attitude you can start to
bring forth right into unconcealed and
conceal a world
that on some level i think it was that
heidegger would say it's
the difference between something being
produced and the
the sense of being something being
accomplished right that
the produce is really tied to produce
the air which is
tied to cause and effect whereas to
accomplish something
i think this is in the letter on
humanism where he says that to
accomplish is to bring something
um into the fullness of its essence and
to bring it
forth into its appearing life and you
can only
accomplish that which is already there
and that which is already always there
is being right so just in that sense of
artistic
bringing forth the world is a
is an understanding that i think is
because i mean it's just
it's rapidly disappearing like it's not
even
and it's not even it's it's it's
disappearing from the
the the intelligibility that people wake
up into
right um and the frame that people live
inside of
one of the things that's striking to me
about vandalism is that
is it it makes no account for itself
right
that it doesn't it doesn't occur for
people
that they're nihilistic and i think this
is doesn't this get into
the difference because there is a
difference between what nietzsche calls
nihilism and what heidegger calls
nihilism isn't there
yeah yeah can you speak to that a little
bit i think that may be
interesting um i mean it depends on
um on so i mean if you come
from heidegger how he interprets
nietzsche and nihilism
in a nutshell it's is that
uh it's it's nothing with beings so
beings themselves
lose their meaning and they become
nothing and that is almost
you know uh consequential to some
trajectory of metaphysics not all of it
so it's not that all of metaphysics is
purely nihilistic or anything but there
is a forgot
an oblivion of negativity and of
the nothing of nihil um as well
and with with heidi what what he calls
in actually in his nietzsche book in the
second volume
he says that there is an authentic
nihilist man
and and that that's the following
it's that's one way so
that's the thinking that
arriving at being means at the same time
being able to let go of it for that
which
one wishes to grasp is
withdrawing and that's
that's the thought of being itself and
in in neighborhood of
the nothing yeah but for nietzsche it's
it's
it's it's concerning it's concerned
really with
with the world with beings
um so as he says for example in
um in the fifth book let me find it
off of the gay science in section
i think uh he says at the end
um so there's a you know he says there's
a terrifying either or
which is now upon europeans which is the
following and i'm
translating from the chairman either you
um abolish
your own ways of honoring god etc or
you abolish yourselves and he says the
letter would be
nihilism um but he's got
other ways so the abolishment of
of the world that would be nihilism but
he's got other ways of
speaking about my life so he speaks of
um
of an active nihilism he speaks of an
incomplete nihilism he speaks of passive
nihilism
so a passive nihilism is as he says
that's a sign of weakness
um the force of spirit is
um is is tired
and no longer does it find
any or it finds is it finds
it its aims or goals and values
that it had up until now spirit utterly
inappropriate
and does not believe in them anymore
and that's a passive nihilism an active
nihilism
as he says can be a sign of strength
and can and this is what he wants and
each niche says nihilism
cannot be avoided it
it it is the history of the next 200
years
and he says somewhere and um heidegger
for example quotes this and the union
coasters as well
that nihilism is the unheimliest gust
the most unhomely the most uncanny
guest at the doors of europe and then he
asked whence does he come
when is does nihilism come
and now so it's that there's no way with
the death of god around nihilism it
means that the horizon has been
wiped away as he says in the madman
section
in the third book of the gay science
but at the same time you know this can
be
of course liberate things like father is
gone right that is
that it can be liberating but what must
occur
in between is a striding through
nihilism
the last man does exactly the opposite
the last man says well
yeah the world is nihilistic it doesn't
nothing means anything um it's all
arbitrary
but it doesn't bother me because i dwell
in my happiness
and i keep increasing my materialistic
happiness
and um i mean lightning has struck right
and lightning has struck a long time ago
yeah that nihilism is is is real
and it's been it's been you know that
you you can look at many different
isms uh as containment strategies
against nihilism and of course nihilism
can also become a consumer good
i mean we have to be very careful not to
turn it into something look look at
nirvana nirvana is one of the best
examples
on the one hand this band from seattle
and and the entire scene
surrounding it you know the grunge kids
from from that
suburbia seattle they they they had
something
to say and they were angry they were
angry with
the 80s and whatever came before and
what happened to their hippie parents
um but it immediately their movement
became
sucked into the machine right i lived 10
blocks away from where where
kurt cobain shot himself
uh and it it's always been striking to
me that the one
what is he gets famous they get famous
with a song it's called smells like
teen spirit that's an interesting title
yeah and then they sing here we are now
entertain us
so you see it doesn't really step out of
it either so
it remains still within
uh so i mean obviously he's he's cynical
here right here we are not entertainers
t
cynical but that's not that's itself so
there is some
an energy there's some for some artistic
force
but it takes still too seriously
this life of the last man and hence gets
sucked into it
and that's nietzsche sees i think you
with nietzsche you can begin to see all
of this
why some and then this is why you know
you know this um that the
my academy is called helkeon
guild academy uh the idea is to come
back to the old guild
model where we have masters
uh in their field um
who who come together and then
teach or converse or
or or hold uh some kind of a conference
or something
and and simply carry forth a certain way
of teaching it's a loose
organization that provides some
protection
and some guidance and it's called
helkeon i always
i pronounce it in the greek way halcyon
i think in english it would be with a c
officially halcyon
and that's a nietzsche very often speaks
of the halcyon bird and if i if i may
maybe
i'll i'll open this just briefly on my
phone because
um i don't want to i've got
weak internet connections here's a quote
from nietzsche that which is really
noble and a work or human being is the
moment when
their sea is smooth and they have
found helsion self-sufficiency
and um another you know
so the helsion bird is
is the iceberg the kingfisher
and the king fisher you've heard of this
bird right
um so let me just say we held sionians
we we held keonians
are devoted to quote from nietzsche
light
feet with fire grave
grand logic stellar dancing
wanton intellectuality the vibrating
light of the south
the calm sea perfection
the tone the tone of of what i'm
aiming and there is a melody to it i'd
like to play a melody
in what i i do and what what we do
together for example right
that that is trus aspiring
to this halcyon tone
to this harmony of the helsinki which is
what so the kingfisher
the iceberg breeds
in winter
in the in a period when
the sea is calm
knowing that the sea won't be calm for
very long
so by the law of the eternal recurrence
of the same
even these horrors that are about to
unfold in january whether
in the mediterranean ocean have
already been overcome it's a very
different temporality
is that you you begin to remember the
future as the past
yeah um that's that's and and the
halcyon tone is exactly the
light feet with we moving beyond that
which is now
taking this here that the over men is a
bridge moving
over because let's come back to the
nirvana example
as much force and energy
and they had energy didn't they as much
as that was there
it got corrupted because it was too
focused on
that which wasn't right now yeah but
that's
that's not that's that's it so it
becomes a play of of of the last man
mentality itself it must move over and
beyond it
and that's exactly what nietzsche says
in the saratha
my i think that's one of my
the the the chapters i uh i i i i love
the most in
severe thrift store is in chairman from
foreign
which in english usually is of is of
passing by or
passing over or moving on depending on
the
translation that you have but if you
hear the
rube again you can hear the uber of the
ubermensch
so it is really over to go over and
beyond
and here's something that happens here
samathustra
comes back to the city this is in the
middle of the books in the third book
um and meets
someone who sounds like him at in the
beginning you think it's this could
almost be sabathus this is someone who
and then but then you realize no no
this the tone here is different you
begin to realize the tone is cynical
right it's like diogenes oh look at me
you know
i'm i'm looking for a human being
because apparently you're the only one
who is
but you know the funny thing about
diogenes is when i said this to
a private student this week is um the
entrepreneurs is so focused on the
police
and on everyone on the market square
that he's completely dependent upon it
right and so he becomes cynical because
no one else is
you know no one else is as good as
diocese no one is good enough for you
uh and this is what this copycat of
sarathustra begins to sound like
very very cynical and savatustra says at
the end
you know he says i i and
nietzsche never has any compassion but
there he's you know he lets
this say you know i feel pity for you
and um and then he says where you can no
longer love
there you shall move over and on
you shall move on you must go over and
beyond
and that that's to me that's the that's
a
a a way of you know aspiring to this
this completely different understanding
of what the over men the evil mensch is
and and this different tone it's
you know nietzsche or sarathustra never
condemns the city
he doesn't like it he doesn't enjoy life
in the city
in the market square but he doesn't say
you know let's burn it to the ground uh
you're all idiots
um but he you know he has his his
moments where he he can be
you know very cynical and and full of
resentment too but not in the
sabathustra
and so it's it's really in because
what are we what's one of the biggest
problems of nihilism now
is of this if this period is nihilism is
of course
resentment right revenge
wanting to tear down instead of wanting
to build yeah
we need a will to build a world that's
meaningful and that that that makes
sense and brings something
forth rather than
you know all these different terms like
the rat race the way i grew up this is
going to be
personal the way i grew up with almost
this kind of it's going to be
terrible when you're old because you
have a shop and it's just a nightmare to
work for a corporation
uh and and so you know you enjoy your
youth
now which just means getting drunk i
guess
and then you move on and then and that's
just gonna be
uh it's it's weird that we have to why
right if if no i mean let's
use these forces uh for force
for liberation and not to have
an extended you know decades-long
existence no but to bring some spark
into the world this sense the sense that
what you said
resentment is what characterizes the the
time of nihilism is resentment
yeah yeah there's something really
interesting going on in the united
states right now
right with these this rioting
that's happening like in the northwest
and stuff is it's unclear
who exactly they're writing against
right there's these big things but it's
uh it's there's an argument
about what they are panning together and
protesting
against like that's just that it's
just that it's a question right
you start to think well what is the
resentment that they're in acting out
for
i think it's almost like it's a
resentment for being resentful
right the object of the resentment is
almost second
second nature but there's a there's a
deep uh that's funny i haven't really
thought about it in these terms but
look there's there's something profound
happening which is um
which i mean we are pushing
towards a future that is increasingly
just a black
wall and
it is it you know it is strange to to be
of the occident to be western
and looking back on thousands of years
now
off of an extended history right i mean
homer the greeks the romans and and
whatever else as americans
would say all this stuff um but so this
extended
uh history nietzsche says this is this
is going to be a
a massive problem uh to
to to be that historical and for him the
contradiction is this
or the trouble is this without history
we are just animals
that's what he says in the use and abuse
of history for life
but with with only history without
anything a historical
it that can destroy us as well and he
makes this distinction between the
antiquarian the critical and the
monumental
and the critical so the monumental
historian
the monumental historian historical
human being
looks at history
and is capable of pulling out
that which is life-affirming and again
that means
to be able to turn everything
into light and flame and of course in
flame you hear
the pur ieee of of heraclitus the
ever-living fire
which with hegel is spirit itself right
so it's turned into light
and and then lights means guidance
it means opening and again again it's
about building that's the monumental
it's life affirming in the sense it sets
strong values um that affirm
life and that always means including
suffering
now the critical historian does not
accept suffering
but looks back and can only find
resentment and of course you know
whether resentment for nietzsche is a
good psychologist
is not being able to live up to the
ideals of some other time
or for the public good that's hard and
it's much easier to just follow
based desires that come you know come
and go
and uh and and to to destroy but
destruction is not infinite
right uh destruction has a certain limit
to itself
it's like a fire yeah you can have
wildfires
and they can burn very long they can
destroy a lot in their way
but they will burn out right and then
they're out
and then they're just out right and some
that's
that's a different fire than the ever
living fire uh
from classes we have to be careful with
that example here
um but yes so it's it's and um
well you know sarathustra it's and he
says though too but one of the things
that
this is this is a quote i actually put
in the syllabus
um because i've it's it's so prescient
this
is from from sarathustra
and i wanted to read the official
translation i mean one of the one of the
one of the chapters begins with the
following quote
wait a second too far into the future
did i
fly dread fell upon me
so that's one and here's another one
not only the reason of millennia that
madness too is breaking out
within us it is dangerous to be
an heir so
nietzsche does see us on on this
precipice on this cliff on this edge
again
the edge against the future uh where
a lot could be breaking out all of a
sudden
it may have been contained um and
that may have been contained by as he
would put it the christian moral
hypothesis
and that's why it's becoming so
extremely important for him to to
set and find new values that are life
affirming
um and and not themselves deeply
nihilistic
the destruction is just always deeply
this is exactly what he describes
nihilism as in
is abolition right it's abolishment
and it's this is uh yeah i mean
though and of course also you know what
you can learn from this passage from
faribagine
of passing of moving on and beyond
uh where the copycat of sabothus were
the cynic
that's you know that that's a resentful
driven
lost little demon um
well what does this little copycat
really need
he needs the city he loathes right
yeah so without without because
what the one thing thing that's not a
thing
what what this what this copycat service
hooster could not do
he could not turn away from it he
couldn't let go
oh he cannot let go
he must the city must exist and it must
exist as something
that he can endlessly criticize um
and rail against and that gives meaning
right i mean
an anti-identity sorry an entire density
can
be can be an identity yeah but
um and this is what it is though right
it's looking for meaning
it's giving meaning yeah hang on one
second i need to pause this
and switch to a light socket my power is
going along
all right thanks for thanks for pausing
for a second i had to find a light
socket
yes so
just to reiterate um the the um
the the ape of sabathustra as he calls
in the copycat
will forever be directed against the
city the police that he wishes to
destroy
yeah that's that's his um identity
that's who he is
and that's the cynical uh with nicholas
the cynical critic
uh critical historian who cannot
affirm life it's always about a struggle
against
something and never about
um um
giving birth i mean nietzsche is is is
i find it more more you know is about
giving birth and letting that
letting go of the tension he's shooting
towards the future
yeah yeah playfully joyfully
yeah reverently you know it's
interesting that as
as you're talking about nietzsche i
could tell that you're in this
in this writing in this this course that
you're doing you've got you're
you're you're these are thoughts that
i'm hearing you talk about with
nietzsche that i haven't heard before
i can tell it's going it's going deeper
um for you with him
but listening to you i keep flashing to
to burning man which on some level i
have always had this sense and burning
man is this
festival that goes on up in literally
the middle of nowhere like the salt
flats
in nevada and i think it's been going on
for since like 1985 or something or
1989 the first time i went was 1995
and it's literally what it is is there's
nothing
it's the most nothing place on the earth
like it's the salt flats that you see on
the commercials where they drive the
cars it's like
at that place and for no no reason
every fourth of july the week of that
fourth of july
people like you know at this point fifty
thousand or
a hundred thousand people show up and
build a city with a man
a wooden man built that at a certain
time burns
and it's just and and and it's just rows
of these
camps and these camps are all these
it's really interesting to think about
so meta it's so funny
it's a lot of these camps are basically
mocking or making up
essentially modernity right like so
you'll have like a
you know somebody will do a camp on say
you know
the church like the the church of trump
right
and then people playing you know play
out some
some characters of you know what a
church of trump would be like right and
then
you know in the middle of it you'll have
like the republican convention right
you know on an acid or something you
know and you have all these
these people play acting and making fun
of in
in these elaborate ways i mean just
brilliant artistic
accomplishments um of basically making
fun of people
who are pretending to do things
meaningfully
and and then it
and then at the midnight or whatever
when the
man burns on that sunday like it does
every year
pete the whole thing surrounds this and
it's like
probably i i have to say i you could pro
it's arguably you could say it's the
most religious experience that
humanity's ever
experienced as this man burns people
are just out of their minds in kind of
um dionysian
frenzies and and it's it's like nobody
really believes
metaphysically that the man represents
anything if anything it represents
whatever's meta from all of that
and there's this humongous relief and
people walk away
i you know i'm in san francisco so i'm
i'm at the
the center of the people basically
produce it so it's like i'm around
people that go to that yeah
i can't tell you how many times i've
heard people talk about
life what life was one way and then they
went to burning man
and then they they came away
and like life was completely different
after that
and i think one of the one of the things
i've always and so here
hearing me talk about
nietzsche's perspective on nihilism and
the way that he talks about that it
almost
it almost sounds like something about
that festival
i don't i doubt it was conscious but but
there's something about that
that festival that seems like almost
like an epitome
of playfulness right of
seeing through the aristocratic
and like all of the
and making fun of it right in these
really meaningful
felt sense ways that i don't i i
that i i can't imagine that there being
more
you know 30 50 000 people
around a burning man going crazy or
all of them in euphoria like i don't
know if there's ever been a religious
event like that
yeah it sounds dionysian yeah
i've not been um but the the way in
which
nietzsche describes dionysus or
the dionysian is
the olympic gods are self-contained
and they are they apollo especially
the god of light and the god of
measurement the god of self knowledge
just much as of dreams
provides a justification of the world
provides a justification of life
and from asia
says dionysus rushes
in and threatens to destroy the olympic
gods
and also threatens to destroy the
the individual
and what is because the the dionysian is
this utter destruction of
the individual and uh just
shows the absurdity of existence shows
the absurdity of
suffering that everything is already
uh well that that death
dwells and everything that that exists
and this almost destroys
the olympic gods however they
welcome him in and make
them one of their own and for nietzsche
you cannot have
just the dionysian to have just the
dionysian would be
that even though there is here you know
there's a reconciliation as he says
between
um man and
and nature and man and beast
that is not in itself
enough it would be it requires always
built what nietzsche calls the grocery
still the grand
style is always the apollonian together
with the dionysian
never just theonises so only that would
be would not be artistic it would not be
tragic it would just be uh orgastic
or too too much of an of uh
of an orgy and
both together that's that's what
generates the great style and that means
measuredness measurement self-knowledge
but not in a socratic sense so socratic
sense would mean to have
total transparency over yourself and
know everything now the know thyself of
the oracle of delphi
is to know your limits and what you're
not supposed to know about yourself
and so that measuredness
and also you know what what you're not
supposed to ask
what you're not supposed to ask about
existence because there are limits
to what what uh a human being can
can stand yeah i mean
history might be too much for some to
bear right ninja actually literally says
this he says
uh history history just the knowledge of
history destroys the weak
that's a quote from nietzsche um but it
always requires both
so the highest form of of existence for
nietzsche is when the apollonian and the
dionysian come together
in a measured way so that there is on
and and not in a
he says not in a back and forth so it's
not you know
the apollonian now and then some
dionysian no
both at the same time
each in their own right um
that means um next to each other
parallel
and the that that's for him that's the
greatest achievement to get to as an as
an artist for example
to be able to be at this level and you
know to some degree you could say you
know it requires some organization with
this
particular festival uh so maybe it comes
together i have not been so i can't
speak to it
um but uh yeah and it there's you know
the the
the the you know what we said so
benignly called leisure
uh scole in greek
in ancient greece that that was very
often uh
orgastic i mean these you know also the
the philosophical dialogues uh
uh the symposium means to drink together
and to let the the spirit of the
wine which is dionysian um
take over to some degree but not only
and that's
so it's this and this of course you know
to some degree it's been
because we live in a very
compartmentalized uh existence right so
this
that's your weekday it's your weekend
that's that's where you do this that's
where you do this
uh so it's it's a fuller
way of being um
would not be burning man 365 days
um but um but
but would would be where all of this
comes together
and it comes together naturally almost
right so
i can't really um i'm thinking about
you know what would a niche chain will
look like that's what i'm thinking about
now i have to think about this a bit
more maybe i'll say something maybe not
but yeah right
totally well it just also seems that
there's um
you know there's that quality of of
you know if you speak to like well why
would you engage in philosophy why would
you read philosophy
right the act of genuinely
considering is opening up to what's
hidden right that
in the sense that there's something of
value in what's hidden
and um
i would say that it seems to me
that i i would imagine something of uh
some when i imagine the nietzschean
world what would a nietzsche that's an
interesting question what would it
look like i i just get the sense that it
has a lot of
relationship to bus to possibility right
that there be that there be a kind of i
don't know of an exaltation but the
sense of
something something grabs your interest
or
a possibility speaks to you that you
have a that there be some kind of
um almost
in all all the levels of love
relationship to
following that and letting it letting it
articulate you as particularly dead
um and the exuberance from
from possibility i would imagine a lot
it would have a lot to do with that
like the future speaking to you right
and letting letting yourself be and i
would have to say that that actually has
been i think
in reading heidegger in this these
conversations
if if there are training for anything it
seems like that's what they're
training for right is
to to just continually
be open to that
you're there's of a horizons of
intelligibility that are concealed to
you
and that and that you can
they can address you right if you can
start to hear them
and um and i think that that's part of
what came through and developed like
developing and circling was very much
it like the influence of heidegger
wasn't so much about like making a
practice that was a heidi gary practice
explicitly it was more like
it was more like grappling with
heidegger allowed me to
un start to see phenomenologically um
and that seeing phenomenologically
happens to be
what a big part of how circling
unfolding
right um and speaking and being able to
listen to people who are always
like kind of getting the sense that
people whenever anybody's
alive they're in response to an
understanding of being
right and so listening to somebody isn't
it's so much listening to them
right it's as it is listening what
they're responding to
right um and and having a conversation
that's about what's unconcealing what's
addressing them
right and they have then they they put
it in terms of like
oh yeah i feel really seen by you or i
feel really understood by you or
something like that but it's not exactly
under it's not exactly understanding
them like an
object that they by which they
understand
it's more like no listening to them is
really
as they're speaking they're speaking to
something and then you
really listen as to is to hear
what they're responding to and
and have it come forth to both of you
and that usually
some version of what we end up talking
about is some possibility that's either
closed and which is affecting them or
some possibility that's
that's opening up that's that's
challenging them in some level that's
usually what the conversation ends up
being about
right so i would imagine that like a
nietzschean world would have something
to do with
an exalted or attuned relationship to
possibility
and flow states
well
it's well he says
when you think of the closing his eyes
listening into the hidden
what is it that that's that's occurring
what what
what's occurring is the most
frightening earthquake and that's the
death of god
this isn't some you know benign event
this is something that we as he says we
only have to begin
to even be able to wake up to
that this has occurred and
this so there is a
there's a sense of horror right and he
needs to speak of the horror of aqui the
horror of emptiness rather than not
wanting at all
the human being wants nothing
and anitchin
and then the will to power if you take
it seriously is
is not just about some you know
someone take taking power or
political power no it's
it means that there's a a field
of force field of insane
power that we can call if you want
that's one other name for what we call
modernity
and that we are now tapping into
and that's how we run these machines
right
by extracting vast amounts of power and
energy
from previously hidden sources
and and by unchanneling them
and at the same time what begins to
occur is
seems to be also some sort of a
weird sameness and turning around
and around itself a repetition
so we are responding to the will to
power and the eternal recurrence of the
same in a way that is
purely technical instrumental
but not artistic if we were to respond
to it artistic
then they can be liberating then we are
not you know why do people speak of the
the hamster wheel or the rat race that
that kind of that
and nietzsche by the way haha in the
posthumously published note somewhere in
1887 or so
he says what's in this is a quote direct
quote well it's inevitably in store for
us today
and that's what the first lecture is
about
is the total economic management of the
earth
so what else
he also says
that what's upon us is the installment
of an unhomely uncanny wheel work
with ever more finely adapted wheels
where the human being is reduced to that
wheel and that's
the instrumental uh rationalistic
response to the will to power which
heidegger then will call the will to
will
right which is another name for
cybernetics
positive feedback loops that can
incorporate
all negativity and turn even those
positive again and
and then of course and then the question
becomes well what's the exit
right this is something many people ask
what's the accent how do you get out
uh because there is this sense of
repetition
of sameness and that lies
somewhere in um
in yeah i mean you could say possibility
it lies somewhere in in
going over and beyond which you could
think of as possibility
and then becoming open to this entirely
other dimension
which also you know which is possible
uh in which we can begin to
as you know he sometimes uses this this
image of the of the
of the ship of sailing towards new
shores
um and then the eternal recurrence of
the same
is no longer crushing
but becomes something liberating because
in
every moment and that's that's what's
it's what's so brutal about it but that
it can become liberating because for
nietzsche there's no way out of
necessity everything is always
necessitated
right that's it does not mean to
rationalize everything is great no it
means to
appreciate understand that
necessity rules over everything
and so and then in every moment
that requires a genuine decision
in your life that recurs in the next
moment
so if in some moment of
decision right we become
negligent and don't act
on our highest as nietzsche we put it
our highest instinct
or our highest uh goals
then that will recur and it will recur
in our
finite existence forever
right right but once you
it but it is forever i mean one of the
one of the clearest ways of
of of saying this is you will be dead
forever i mean this is your finitude in
eternity
um and it will recur in your finite
existence forevermore
and so in the moment that you just
described off
of you know being you know i'm i feel
seen i feel listened to etc
that can become a moment of making the
next moment the highest
and that will recur so that the next
highest next moment
is again a highest and then it's a light
play right so it's elevating itself
because it's recurring within itself and
that's when it becomes meaningful
it doesn't mean that you're you live
forever it doesn't mean that's not what
it means
um but we are trapped in this reputation
anyways
right i mean um
you know even though there is now is a
pandemic etc people work from home the
written the so-called rat race hamster
reel continues
um and why is it that it's described as
a wheel well it is an uncanny
wheel work where we are finally adapted
wheels
and uh we are reduced and reduced to
cannon fodder
or as marx puts a reserve army
uh standing ready to be exploited
um but there is for nietzsche
there is deposit not for everyone
obviously but phoenicians not for
everyone
nietzsche is not an egalitarian that
should be very clear
for nietzsche it's it's it's a few uh
who can
and they will be able to um
to live up to this highest
uh in their own being but it's still in
a finite existence
and it is about what you know you
how you find the stance in to speak with
hiding in the midst of beings
um and it's there are consequences to
thinking there are consequences to
actions
there are consequences to decisions
because they're not just mere choices
you know like a consumption choice it's
a it's a
it's like it's a judgment and that
judgment lead to
leads to another judgment and that
becomes your exit that becomes your life
yeah and then of course the question is
can you affirm it here's a beautiful
quote from nietzsche
if you become young when you're old
you will stay young for a very long time
because some people the thinking kinds
you know they are very old and they're
very young
um as you might know and
and here's here's something here's
here's a slogan
um there's not from nietzsche he's a
neither house
you know if you live your own life it is
very
long and full flowing and rich
if you don't it is very short and then
it must be extended and prolonged etc
because that which is there is not
coming out
yeah and you can see it but you can see
when it's not coming out with people
and that's perhaps also describing oh i
feel seen
because there is the moment something
that's coming out all of a sudden yeah
what's that you said you are a finitude
in eternity
yeah no you you will be deaf forever
right uh but that's
that's that that's just uh that's a bit
of a that's a bit of a
bit of a a joke but no but in in
in your finite existence i mean think
think about it in your finite existence
within that finitude everything recurs
forever
yeah yeah so you you better respond
in a way that you can allow this to
recur forever because what how
so much of what you know uh neurosis
uh and and you know which are
or that i'm not speaking about you know
severe uh
cases of psychiatric
uh uh malaise that
that can befall people and maybe a
neurosis what is it it's something
that's being suppressed
um and it's being suppressed con repeat
repetitively you know psychologists
speak of patterns
right they speak of let's break a
pattern here let's what's your
pattern let's break it etc well you know
a pattern that's
that's too well what is it there's
something being repeated the entire time
and that can be just one decision made
once that then repeats itself in every
single moment
and it's in psychologically it's it's
self-fulfilling prophecy
it's a visualization etc that can lead
to the ever same
results if you like all the time but
with nietzsche or with you know with a
philosophy it's just
it's it's richer because it comes from
it's not just you
as a case who's doing something wrong it
has to do with time
and how we understand time and what kind
of
temporality we are in the temporality
that that
heineken will call ecstatic temporality
that's exactly eternal recurrence of the
same
properly understood because that which
has been
is coming towards you
and that becomes your presence right
that becomes what gifts itself as the
presence there's a wonderful film called
arrival
where you know hollywood being hollywood
they have to make it about aliens
um but they have a non
it's a profound movie i love that movie
yeah yeah they have a they have um
i mean that film is about the eternal
recurrence of the same
right and it's about ecstatic time and
what is it that happens to the main
character
she begins to remember the future
as her past yeah by what
by reading and translating
non-propositional non-linear language
yeah yeah i mean look if it weren't a
hollywood film it wouldn't be aliens it
would just be
a few people sitting down together
trying to write poetry like hillary did
um and nietzsche did yeah that lets you
too far into the future did i fly dread
fell upon me what
some of the spookiest things here's
something spooky from heidegger
he says in his lecture course on plato
on alithea it's up to us as much as to
plato
to make sure that alethia is not
something of the past but becomes our
genuine history
take the first half it's up to us as
much as to plato
i mean this is this is this is extremely
weird right because
when you listen to this carefully what
he's actually saying is
we are we can be in the same sphere as
this man still because this way of
thinking and this comes back to what we
said before
think thoughts that guide thoughts that
come on dove's feet
guide the world so we we can be in these
spheres
where plato is still speaking because
these thoughts
still move everything i mean if you read
the cave and you don't think that that's
what we're living in
um then then nothing can help you uh but
um but
sorry first you know but then uh
but here so what would the nietzschean
world look like it would look like
you you are you know kind of led into
uh not a dollar universe that's just
expanding
but but but a self-contained cosmos that
he says
and as heraclitus says also has no
beginning
and no ending and you are a finite
instantiation
of these movements of time where
everything
will always already have happened
but you and you we can tap into this or
find lean into it find it tear it open
through and then through a different
understanding
of language and then you you know you
begin to remember yourself differently
right maybe this is also something
that's happening in circling is that
what does it mean to be seen
it's because all of a sudden you're seen
in a different way
and that but to be seen means to have
any sort of
like a sense of who you are how do you
have a sense of who you are is by
remembering who you are
but to be seen means to begin to
remember yourself differently yeah
yeah yeah exactly
i just had to thought about it in the
world as one
which the world becomes
you can re you the world in such a way
right that's similar to that
right of of the text being this alien
text right
it's non-proposition alien text it just
struck me of like oh yeah
it's about to be in a nature world is to
read the world
as that kind of a text right
yeah it's to it
and not just arbitrarily right i mean
this isn't this isn't about
um you know dolly's books about
nietzsche's writing his own life etc
but that's psychologically interesting
and it's biographically important
perhaps but
if you take thinking seriously the
nietzsche does
stand in a certain tradition and has to
wrestle with it
and and also sees something about what
is coming i mean he says at some point
what is coming now
is the historical sense yeah
yeah yeah
and that that means
max themes and reflections that history
is the weight of mutual assessment
we must be able to forget to actively
forget
um and because what
isn't it strange we live in this
almost frozen time where
you can just gaze back upon the
millennia and just
pick and choose whatever you darn well
wish you know
some ism here some some some peace from
over there
and why is this all becoming available
but like like the entire
planet is a museum yeah
yes it could be inventoried right and
presented
yeah we had the inventory before we
started this yeah exactly
so you see you can you can you can use
um
something like youtube to uh to start
a ch an inventory channel shall we
um here's the here's a philosophical
inventory
um or you can generate
something um that's in that sense
artistic
dionysian but apollonian as well
because it tries to find its own measure
within itself
and lets something spontaneously occur
right we
have no idea we'll sit down okay let's
talk about nietzsche but
uh so we never know what's what's coming
of it
yeah and there's not much inventory i'm
sorry to anyone who's still listening
right totally i tell you what
make sure email me what you want me to
put on the on the thing
yes sir yes sir thank you very much
any any last things you want to say
about the course and i'll put all the
links
um in the show notes yeah uh well first
of all thank you very much
i look forward to to to you guy and then
to everybody else who listened
um and uh yeah guy i think you
you'll join in sometimes from time to
time the seminars whenever you've got
the time
uh and i would be you know if people
have any questions they can email me
um and yeah i would be really i'm really
grateful to have
a couple of of your listeners too on
on the course and read some niche
together for the next it's going to be
intense seven weeks
so yeah thank you thanks sir signing off
bye ciao